{"test_questions": [[{"question": "Question:  In which year was Rahul born ?\nStatements:\n\nRahul at present is 25 years younger to his mother.\nRahul's brother, who was born in 1964, is 35 years younger to his mother.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From both I and II, we find that Rahul is (35 - 25) = 10 years older than his brother, who was born in 1964. So, Rahul was born in 1954."}, {"question": "Question:  What will be the total weight of 10 poles, each of the same weight ?\nStatements:\n\nOne-fourth of the weight of each pole is 5 kg.\nThe total weight of three poles is 20 kilograms more than the total weight of two poles.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that weight of each pole = (4x5) kg = 20 kg.So, total weight of 10 poles = (20 x 10) kg = 200 kg.From II, we conclude that:Weight of each pole = (weight of 3 poles) - (weight of 2 poles) = 20 kg.So, total weight of 10 pojes = (20 x 10) kg = 200 kg."}, {"question": "Question:  How many children does M have ?\nStatements:\n\nH is the only daughter of X who is wife of M.\nK and J are brothers of M.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that H is the only daughter of M. But this does not indicate that M has no son. The information given in II is immaterial."}, {"question": "Question:  How much was the total sale of the company ?\nStatements:\n\nThe company sold 8000 units of product A each costing Rs. 25.\nThis company has no other product line.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, total sale of product A = Rs. (8000 x 25) = Rs. 200000.From II, we know that the company deals only in product A.This implies that sale of product A is the total sale of the company, which is Rs. 200000."}, {"question": "Question:  The last Sunday of March, 2006 fell on which date ?\nStatements:\n\nThe first Sunday of that month fell on 5th.\nThe last day of that month was Friday.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that 5th, 12th, 19th and 26th of March, 2006 were Sundays.So, the last Sunday fell on 26th.From II, we conclude that 31st March, 2006 was Friday. Thus, 26th March, 2006 was the last Sunday of the month."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the code for 'sky' in the code language ?\nStatements:\n\nIn the code language, 'sky is clear' is written as 'de ra fa'.\nIn the same code language, 'make it clear' is written as 'de ga jo'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The only word common to I and II is 'clear' and as such, only the code for 'clear' can be ascertained from the given information."}, {"question": "Question:  How many children are there between P and Q in a row of children ?\nStatements:\n\nP is fifteenth from the left in the row.\nQ is exactly in the middle and there are ten children towards his right.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From II, Q being in the middle, there are 10 children to his right as well as to his left. So, Q is 11th from the left. From I, P is 15th from the left.Thus, from both I and II, we conclude that there are 3 children between P and Q."}, {"question": "Question:  How is T related to K?\nStatements:\n\nR's sister J has married Ts brother L, who is the only son of his parents.\nK is the only daughter of L and J.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we know that L is T's brother and J's husband. Since L is the only son of his parents, T is L's sister.From II, we know that K is L's daughter.Thus, from I and II, we conclude that T is the sister of K's father i.e. T is K's aunt."}, {"question": "Question:  How is J related to P ?\nStatements:\n\nM is brother of P and T is sister of P.\nP's mother is married to J's husband who has one son and two daughters.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From II, we know that P's mother is married to J's husband, which means that J is P's mother."}, {"question": "Question:  How is X related to Y ?\nStatements:\n\nY and Z are children of D who is wife of X.\nR's sister X is married to Ys father.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Y is the child of D who is wife of X i.e. X is Y's father.From II, X is married to Y's father. This implies that X is Y's mother."}, {"question": "Question:  Who is to the immediate right of P among five persons P, Q, R, S and T facing North ?\nStatements:\n\nR is third to the left of Q and P is second to the right of R.\nQ is to the immediate left of T who is second to the right of P.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we have the order: R, -, P, Q.From II, we have the order: P, Q, T.Clearly, each one of the above two orders indicates that Q is to the immediate right of P."}, {"question": "Question:  On which date of the month was Anjali born in February 2004 ?\nStatements:\n\nAnjali was born on an even date of the month.\nAnjali's birth date was a prime number.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I and II, we conclude that Anjali was born in February 2004 on a date which is an even prime number. Since the only even prime number is 2, so Anjali was born on 2nd February, 2004."}, {"question": "Question:  How is X related to Y?\nStatements:\n\nY says, \"I have only one brother\".\nX says, \"I have only one sister\".", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "The statements in I and II do not provide any clue regarding relation between X and Y."}, {"question": "Question:  How is F related to P?\nStatements:\n\nP has two sisters M and N.\nF's mother is sister of M's father.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I and II, we conclude that P is M's brother and so M's father is P's father. So, F is the child of the sister of P's father i.e. F's mother is P's aunt or F is P's cousin."}, {"question": "Question:  B is the brother of A. How is A related to B ?\nStatements:\n\nA is the sister of C.\nE is the husband of A.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "B is A's brother means A is either brother or sister of B. Now, each one of I and II individually indicates that A is a female, which means that A is B's sister."}, {"question": "Question:  How many children are there in the row of children facing North ?\nStatements:\n\nVishakha who is fifth from the left end is eighth to the left of Ashish who is twelfth from the right end.\nRohit is fifth to the left of Nisha who is seventh from the right end and eighteenth from the left end.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Since 8th to the left of 12th from the right is 20th from the right, so from I, we know that Vishakha is 5th from left and 20th from right i.e. there are 4 children to the left and 19 to the right of Vishakha. So, there are (4 + 1 + 19) i.e. 24 children in the row.From II, Nisha is 7th from right and 18th from left end of the row.So, there are (6 + 1 + 17) = 24 children in the row."}, {"question": "Question:  How many doctors are practising in this town ?\nStatements:\n\nThere is one doctor per seven hundred residents.\nThere are 16 wards with each ward having as many doctors as the number of wards.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From I, total number of doctors in town = (1/700 x N) , where N = total number of residents in town. But, the value of N is not known.From II, total number of doctors in town= (Number of wards in town) x (Number of doctors in each ward)= 16 x 16 = 256."}, {"question": "Question:  On which day of the week was birthday of Sahil ?\nStatements:\n\nSahil celebrated his birthday the very next day on which Arun celebrated his birthday.\nThe sister of Sahil was born on the third day of the week and two days after Sahil was born.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "I does not mention the day of the week on the birthday of either Arun or Sahil.According to II, Sahil's sister was born on Wednesday and Sahil was born two days before Wednesday i.e. on Monday."}, {"question": "Question:  How many pages of book X did Robert read on Sunday ?\nStatements:\n\nThe book has 300 pages out of which two-thirds were read by him before Sunday.\nRobert read the last 40 pages of the book on the morning of Monday.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I and II, we find that Robert read (300 x 2/3) i.e. 200 pages before Sunday and the last 40 pages on Monday.This means that he read [300 - (200 + 40)] i.e. 60 pages on Sunday."}, {"question": "Question:  How is Tanya related to the man in the photograph ?\nStatements:\n\nMan in the photograph is the only son of Tanya's grandfather.\nThe man in the photograph has no brothers or sisters and his father is Tanya's grandfather.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that the man is the only son of Tanya's grandfather i.e. he is Tanya's father or Tanya is the man's daughter.From II, we conclude that the man's father is Tanya's grandfather. Since the man has no brothers or sisters, so he is Tanya's father or Tanya is the man's daughter."}, {"question": "Question:  Among T, V, B, E and C, who is the third from the top when arranged in the descending order of their weights ?\nStatements:\n\nB is heavier than T and C and is less heavier than V who is not the heaviest.\nC is heavier than only T.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From I, we have: B > T, B > C, V > B. Thus, V is heavier than each one of B, T and C. But V is not the heaviest. So, E is the heaviest.Thus, we have the order. E>V>B>T>C or E>V>B>C>T. Clearly, B is third from the top."}, {"question": "Question:  Which word in the code language means 'flower' ?\nStatements:\n\n'de fu la pane' means 'rose flower is beautiful' and 'la quiz' means 'beautiful tree'.\n'de la chin' means 'red rose flower' and 'pa chin' means 'red tea'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From the two statements given in I, the code for the only common word 'beautiful' can be determined.From the two statements given in II, the code for the only common word 'red' can be determined.In I and II, the common words are 'rose and 'flower' and the common code words are 'de' and 'la'. So, the code for 'flower' is either 'de' or 'la'."}, {"question": "Question:  How many students in a class play football ?\nStatements:\n\nOnly boys play football.\nThere are forty boys and thirty girls in the class.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "It is not mentioned whether all the boys or a proportion of them play football."}, {"question": "Question:  Who is C's partner in a game of cards involving four players A, B, C and D ?\nStatements:\n\nD is sitting opposite to A.\nB is sitting right of A and left of D.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "Clearly, each of the given statements shows that B is sitting opposite to C or B is the partner of C."}, {"question": "Question:  On a T.V. channel, four serials A, B, C and D were screened, one on eacn day, on four consecutive days but not necessarily in that order. On which day was the serial C screened ?\nStatements:\n\nThe first serial was screened on 23rd, Tuesday and was followed by serial D.\nSerial A was not screened on 25th and one serial was screened between serials A and B.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we know that the serials were screened on 23rd, 24th, 25th and 26th.Clearly, D was screened second i.e. on 24th, Wednesday.From II, we know that one serial was screened between A and B.So, A and B were screened first and third, i.e. on 23rd and 25th. But, A was not screened on 25th.So, A was screened on 23rd and B on 25th. Thus, C was screened on 26th, Friday."}, {"question": "Question:  How is Sulekha related to Nandini ?\nStatements:\n\nSulekha's husband is the only son of Nandini's mother.\nSulekha's brother and Nandini's husband are cousins.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Sulekha is the wife of Nandini's mother's only son i.e. Nandini's brother. Thus, Sulekha is Nandini's sister-in-law.From II, we conclude that Sulekha is the cousin of Nandini's husband, which implies that Sulekha is Nandini's sister-in-law."}, {"question": "Question:  Can Ritesh retire from office X in January 2006, with full pension benefits ?\nStatements:\n\nRitesh will complete 30 years of service in office X in April 2000 and desires to retire.\nAs per office X rules, an employee has to complete minimum 30 years of service and attain age of 60. Ritesh has 3 years to complete age of 60.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the facts given in I and II contain two conditions to be fulfilled to get retirement and also indicate that Ritesh fulfills only one condition out of them."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the code for 'or' in the code language?\nStatements:\n\n'nik sa te' means 'right or wrong', 'ro da nik' means 'he is right' and 'fe te ro' means 'that is wrong'.\n'pa nik la' means 'that right man', 'sa ne pa' means 'this or that' and 'ne ka re' means 'tell this there'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "I. In 'right or wrong' and 'he is right', the common word is 'right' and the common code word is 'nik'. So 'nik' means 'right'. In 'right or wrong' and 'that is wrong', the common word is 'wrong' and the common code word is 'te'. So, 'te' means 'wrong'.Thus, in 'right or wrong', 'sa' is the code for 'or'. II. In 'that right man' and 'this or that', the common word is 'that' and the common code word is 'pa'. So, 'pa' means 'that'. In 'this or that' and 'tell this there', the common word is 'this' and the common code word is 'ne'. So, 'ne' means 'this'. Thus, in 'this or that', 'sa' is the code for 'or'."}, {"question": "Question:  Madan is elder than Kamal and Sharad is younger than Arvind. Who among them is the youngest ?\nStatements:\n\nSharad is younger than Madan.\nArvind is younger than Kamal.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "As given, we have: M > K, A > S.From II, K > A. Thus, we have: M > K > A > S.So, Sharad is the youngest. From I, M > S. Thus, we have: M>K>A>S or M>A>K>S or M>A>S>K."}, {"question": "Question:  On which date in August was Kapil born ?\nStatements:\n\nKapil's mother remembers that Kapil was born before nineteenth but after fifteenth.\nKapil's brother remembers that Kapil was born before seventeenth but after twelfth.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Kapil was born on any one of the dates among 16th, 17th and 18th.From II, we conclude that Kapil was born on any one of the dates among 13th, 14th, 15th and 16th.Thus, from both I and II, we conclude that Kapil was born on 16th August."}, {"question": "Question:  What is Gagan's age ?\nStatements:\n\nGagan, Vimal and Kunal are all of the same age.\nTotal age of Vimal, Kunal and Anil is 32 years and Anil is as old as Vimal and Kunal together.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "As given in I and II, we have: G = V = K, V + K + A = 32 and A = V + K.Putting V + K = A in V + K + A = 32, we have: 2A = 32 or A = 16.Thus, V + K = 16 and V = K. So, V = K = 8. Thus, G = 8."}, {"question": "Question:  In a certain code, '13' means 'stop smoking' and '59' means 'injurious habit'. What do '9' and '5' mean respectively in that code ?\nStatements:\n\n'157' means 'stop bad habit'.\n'839' means 'smoking is injurious'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "'59' means 'injurious habit' and '157' means 'stop bad habit' (from I). Thus, the common code number '5' stands for common word 'habit'. So, '9' represents 'injurious'. Hence, I is sufficient.Also, '59' means 'injurious habit' and '839' means 'smoking is injurious'. Thus, the common code number '9' stands for common word 'injurious'. So, '5' represents 'habit'. Thus, II is also sufficient.,"}, {"question": "Question:  How much money do Vivek and Suman have together ?\nStatements:\n\nSuman has 20 rupees less than what Tarun has.\nVivek has 30 rupees more than what Tarun has.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I, we have: S = T - 20.From II, we have: V = T + 30.Thus, from both I and II, we have: V + S = (T + 30) + (T - 20) = (2 T + 10).So, to get the required amount, we need to know the amount that Tarun has."}, {"question": "Question:  Among Monika, Anita, Sonal, Ratna and Tanvy, who came last for the programme ?\nStatements:\n\nMonika came after Anita but not after Tanvy.\nRatna came after Tanvy but not after Sonal.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From I, we have the order : A, M, T.From II, we have the order: T, R, S.Combining the above two, we get the order: A, M, T, R, S.Thus, Sonal came last for the programme."}, {"question": "Question:  Who among P, Q, R, S and T is the lightest?\nStatements:\n\nR is heavier than Q and T but lighter than S.\nS is not the heaviest.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I, we have: R>Q, R>T, S>R i.e. S>R>Q>T or S>R>T>Q.From II, S is not the heaviest. So, P is the heaviest. Thus, we have: P > S > R > Q > T or P > S > R > T > Q. Hence, either T or Q is the lightest."}, {"question": "Question:  How is T related to K?\nStatements:\n\nK has two sons; one of the sons is A.\nThe mother of T has only two sons - Aand B.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From II, we know that T's mother has only two sons, A and B. This implies that T is the sister of both A and B. But, from I, A is also K's son. So, T is the daughter of K."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the shortest distance between Devipur and Durgapur ?\nStatements:\n\nDurgapur is 20 kms away from Rampur.\nDevipur is 15 kms away from Rampur.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Clearly, the distance of each village from Rampur is given in I and II. But nothing about their relative positions is mentioned. So, the distance between the two villages cannot be calculated."}, {"question": "Question:  How is A related to D ?\nStatements:\n\nB is the brother of A.\nB is D's son.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "From I and II, we conclude that A is either son or daughter of D."}, {"question": "Question:  Manoj, Prabhakar, Akash and Kamal are four friends. Who among them is the heaviest ?\nStatements:\n\nPrabhakar is heavier than Manoj and Kamal but lighter than Akash.\nManoj is lighter than Prabhakar and Akash but heavier than Kamal.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From I, we have: P > M, P > K, A > P.Thus, A > P > M > K or A > P > K > M. So, Akash is the heaviest.From II, we have: P > M, A > M, M > K.Thus, A > P > M > K or P > A > M > K. So, either Akash or Prabhakar is the heaviest."}, {"question": "Question:  Vinod's and Javed's salaries are in the proportion of 4 : 3 respectively. What is Vinod's salary ?\nStatements:\n\nJaved's salary is 75% that of Vinod's salary.\nJaved's salary is Rs 4500.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "B", "explanation": "Statement I is merely an interpretation of the information contained in the question.However, Vinod's salary can be ascertained from II as follows : Let Vinod's and Javed's salaries be 4x and 3x respectively. Then, 3x = 4500 or x = 1500. Therefore Vinod's salary = 4x = Rs. 6000."}, {"question": "Question:  What is Nitin's rank from the top in a class of forty students ?\nStatements:\n\nThere are ten students between Nitin and Deepak.\nDeepak is twentieth from the top.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "Since there are ten students between Nitin and Deepak, so Nitin may be eleven ranks above or below Deepak. Thus, Nitin may be 9th or 31st from the top."}, {"question": "Question:  Which direction is Sunny facing now ?\nStatements:\n\nIf Sunny turns to his right and again turns to his right, he will be facing North.\nIf Sunny walks some distance and turns left and again walks some distance, then his face will be towards left of Dinesh who is facing South.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Sunny is facing South, since a person facing South shall face North on turning to his right, twice.From II, we know that after walking, Sunny shall face towards left of Dinesh facing South i.e. East and a person walking southwards shall face East on turning to 'his left.Thus, Sunny is facing South."}, {"question": "Question:  T studies in which of the schools B, C, D, E and F ?\nStatements:\n\nT does not study in the same school as either R or J.\nR and J study in schools D and F respectively.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "D", "explanation": "As given in I and II, R studies in school D and J studies in school F. So, T does not study in school D or school F. Thus, T studies in any one of the schools B, C or E."}, {"question": "Question:  How is Divya related to Shaloo ?\nStatements:\n\nDivya's mother is sister of Shaloo's father.\nShaloo is the daughter of Divya's grandfather's only child.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that Divya's mother is Shaloo's aunt or Divya is Shaloo's cousin.Now, Divya's grandfather's only child is Divya's parent. So, from II, we conclude that Shaloo and Divya are daughters of the same parents i.e. Divya is Shaloo's sister."}, {"question": "Question:  How many New Year's greeting cards were sold this year in your shop ?\nStatements:\n\nLast year 2935 cards were sold.\nThe number of cards sold this year was 1.2 times that of last year.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "From both I and II, we find that the number of cards sold this year = (2935 x 1.2) = 3522."}, {"question": "Question:  On which day in April is Gautam's birthday?\nStatements:\n\nGautam was born exactly 28 years after his mother was born.\nHis mother will be 55 years 4 months and 5 days on August 18 this year.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "Clearly, the birthday of Gautam's mother can be found out from II and then Gautam's birthday can be determined using the fact given in I."}, {"question": "Question:  What is the code for 'is' in the code language ?\nStatements:\n\nIn the code language, 'shi tu ke' means 'pen is blue'.\nIn the same code language, 'ke si re' means 'this is wonderful'.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "E", "explanation": "In I and II, the common word is 'is' and the common code word is 'ke'. So, 'ke' is the code for 'is'."}, {"question": "Question:  Among A, B, C, D and E, who is in the middle while standing in a row ?\nStatements:\n\nC, who is third to the left of D, is to the immediate right of A and second to the left of E.\nC is second to the left of E, who is not at any of the ends and who is third to the right of A. D is at one of the ends.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "C", "explanation": "From each one of I and II, we get the order : A, C, B, E, D. Clearly, B is in the middle."}, {"question": "Question:  Among A, B, C, D, E and F, who is the heaviest ?\nStatements:\n\nA and D are heavier than B, E and F but none of them is the heaviest.\nA is heavier than D but lighter than C.", "opta": "I alone is sufficient while II alone is not sufficient", "optb": "II alone is sufficient while I alone is not sufficient", "optc": "Either I or II is sufficient", "optd": "Neither I nor II is sufficient", "opte": "Both I and II are sufficient", "ans": "A", "explanation": "From I, we conclude that since none of A and D is the heaviest and each one of B, E and F is lighter than both A and D, so C is the heaviest."}]]}